suppose you have a square that has a
side length of one
then the diagonal line that cuts through
the square has a length given by the
square root of 2 by the Pythagorean
theorem
here's a related question what if we
start with a regular pentagon with side
length one what's the length x of the
diagonal cutting through this shape
let's find out using a visual proof
first we draw a second diagonal line
like this which creates this shaded
isosceles triangle when we draw another
diagonal like this we create a second
triangle shaded in red that's a
subtriangle of the blue triangle
now if we consider the three pictured
angles where the top one is labeled
Alpha and we draw the circumscribed
circle we see that Alpha is subtended by
an arc and so are the other two pictured
angles with question marks but all three
of those arcs are exactly one-fifth of
the entire circle and therefore each of
the angles must be Alpha this also means
that the other angle that is in the blue
triangle and the red triangle must be 2
times Alpha
but now the four pictured angles give us
the full measure of the triangle so we
see that 5 times Alpha must be 180
degrees and therefore Alpha must be 36
degrees but this then means that both of
the pictured triangles the blue and the
red have 36 degree angles and 272 degree
angles and both of them are therefore
isosceles triangles but it turns out
that we also see we have a third
triangle shaded in green here this
triangle has two 36 degree angles and
therefore it is isosceles as well
using the fact that these three
triangles are isosceles we can see that
this side length here is one so that the
short side length on the red triangle is
x minus 1.
but now we can use the fact that the two
triangles shown the red and the blue are
similar as they have exactly the same
angle measurements
the fact that the two triangles are
similar means that the ratio of their
side lengths are equal so that x divided
by one must equal 1 divided by x minus
one now when we clear denominators we
get that x times x minus 1 equals one
and this means that x squared minus x
minus 1 is equal to zero this equation
has two roots and only one of them is
positive which is x equals Phi which is
the golden ratio
therefore the length of the diagonal in
this regular pentagon with side length 1
must be Phi the golden ratio
here's a cool way to use this diagram
let's suppose that the golden ratio is
rational that means that it can be
written as a ratio of two integers say A
over B and let's assume that this ratio
is in lowest terms
the fact that Phi equals A over B means
that there is a regular pentagon like
this where the diagonal is length a and
the side length of the Pentagon is B
once again we can swing the side length
down like this to see that the small
subtriangle created inside the larger
triangle pictured here must have length
a minus B but once again these two
triangles are similar and therefore A
over B must be equal to B over a minus B
but Phi equals A over B so that means
Phi equals B over a minus B and this is
a contradiction because B is less than a
and a minus B is less than b so this
contradicts that we had Phi in lowest
terms when we wrote it as A over B but
that means our original assumption was
wrong so that the golden ratio fee
cannot be written as the ratio of two
integer values and so the golden ratio
is irrational